对于很多机器学习算法 包括线性回归、逻辑回归、神经网络等等
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
For many learning algorithms, among them linear regression, logistic regression and neural networks,
算法的实现都是通过得出某个代价函数 或者某个最优化的目标来实现的
the way we derive the algorithm was by coming up with a cost function or coming up with an optimization objective.
然后使用梯度下降这样的方法来求得代价函数的最小值
And then using an algorithm like gradient descent to minimize that cost function.
当我们的训练集较大时 梯度下降算法则显得计算量非常大
We have a very large training set gradient descent becomes a computationally very expensive procedure.
在这段视频中 我想介绍一种跟普通梯度下降不同的方法 随机梯度下降(stochastic gradient descent)
In this video, we'll talk about a modification to the basic gradient descent algorithm called Stochastic gradient descent,
用这种方法我们可以将算法运用到较大训练集的情况中
which will allow us to scale these algorithms to much bigger training sets.
假如你要使用梯度下降法来训练某个线性回归模型
Suppose you are training a linear regression model using gradient descent.
简单复习一下 我们的假设函数是这样的
As a quick recap, the hypothesis will look like this, and the cost function will look like this,
代价函数是你的假设在训练集样本上预测的平均平方误差的二分之一倍的求和
which is the sum of one half of the average square error of your hypothesis on your m training examples,
通常我们看到的代价函数都是像这样的弓形函数
and the cost function we've already seen looks like this sort of bow-shaped function.
因此 画出以θ0和θ1为参数的代价函数J 就是这样的弓形函数
So, plotted as function of the parameters theta 0 and theta 1, the cost function J is a sort of a bow-shaped function.
这就是梯度下降算法 在内层循环中
And gradient descent looks like this, where in the inner loop of gradient descent
你需要用这个式子反复更新参数θ的值
you repeatedly update the parameters theta using that expression.
在这段视频剩下的时间里 我将依然以线性回归为例
Now in the rest of this video, I'm going to keep using linear regression as the running example.
但随机梯度下降的思想也可以应用于其他的学习算法
But the ideas here, the ideas of Stochastic gradient descent is fully general and also applies to other learning algorithms
比如逻辑回归、神经网络或者其他依靠梯度下降来进行训练的算法中
like logistic regression, neural networks and other algorithms that are based on training gradient descent on a specific training set.
这张图表示的是梯度下降的做法 这个点表示了参数的初始位置
So here's a picture of what gradient descent does, if the parameters are initialized to the point there
那么在你运行梯度下降的过程中 多步迭代最终会将参数锁定到全局最小值
then as you run gradient descent different iterations of gradient descent will take the parameters to the global minimum.
步进的轨迹看起来非常快地收敛到全局最小
So take a trajectory that looks like that and heads pretty directly to the global minimum.
而梯度下降法的问题是 当m值很大时
Now, the problem with gradient descent is that if m is large.
计算这个微分项的计算量就变得很大 因为需要对所有m个训练样本求和
Then computing this derivative term can be very expensive, because the surprise, summing over all m examples.
所以假如m的值为3亿 美国就有3亿人口
So if m is 300 million, alright. So in the United States, there are about 300 million people.
美国的人口普查数据就有这种量级的数据记录
And so the US or United States census data may have on the order of that many records.
所以如果想要为这么多数据拟合一个线性回归模型的话 那就需要对所有这3亿数据进行求和
So you want to fit the linear regression model to that then you need to sum over 300 million records.
这样的计算量太大了 这种梯度下降算法也被称为批量梯度下降(batch gradient descent)
And that's very expensive. To give the algorithm a name, this particular version of gradient descent is also called Batch gradient descent.
“批量”就表示我们需要每次都考虑所有的训练样本
And the term Batch refers to the fact that we're looking at all of the training examples at a time.
我们可以称为所有这批训练样本
We call it sort of a batch of all of the training examples.
也许这不是个恰当的名字 但做机器学习的人就是这么称呼它的
And it really isn't the, maybe the best name but this is what machine learning people call this particular version of gradient descent.
想象一下 如果你真的有这3亿人口的数据存在硬盘里
And if you imagine really that you have 300 million census records stored away on disc.
那么这种算法就需要把所有这3亿人口数据读入计算机 仅仅就为了算一个微分项而已
The way this algorithm works is you need to read into your computer memory all 300 million records in order to compute this derivative term.
你需要将这些数据连续传入计算机 因为计算机存不下那么大的数据量
You need to stream all of these records through computer because you can't store all your records in computer memory.
所以你需要很慢地读取数据 然后计算一个求和 再来算出微分
So you need to read through them and slowly, you know, accumulate the sum in order to compute the derivative.
所有这些做完以后 你才完成了一次梯度下降的迭代
And then having done all that work, that allows you to take one step of gradient descent.
然后你又需要重新来一遍
And now you need to do the whole thing again.
也就是再读取这3亿人口数据 做个求和
You know, scan through all 300 million records, accumulate these sums.
然后做完这些 你又完成了梯度下降的一小步
And having done all that work, you can take another little step using gradient descent.
然后再做一次 你得到第三次迭代 等等
And then do that again. And then you take yet a third step. And so on.
所以 要让算法收敛 绝对需要花很长的时间
And so it's gonna take a long time in order to get the algorithm to converge.
相比于批量梯度下降 我们介绍的方法就完全不同了
In contrast to Batch gradient descent, what we are going to do is come up with a different algorithm
这种方法在每一步迭代中 不用考虑全部的训练样本
that doesn't need to look at all the training examples in every single iteration,
只需要考虑一个训练样本
but that needs to look at only a single training example in one iteration.
在开始介绍新的算法之前 我把批量梯度下降算法再写在这里
Before moving on to the new algorithm, here's just a Batch gradient descent algorithm written out again
这里是代价函数 这里是迭代的更新过程
with that being the cost function and that being the update and of course this term here,
梯度下降法中的这一项
that's used in the gradient descent rule, that is the partial derivative
是最优化目标 代价函数Jtrain(θ) 关于参数θj的偏微分
with respect to the parameters theta J of our optimization objective, J train of theta.
下面我们来看更高效的这种方法
Now, let's look at the more efficient algorithm that scales better to large data sets.
为了更好地描述随机梯度下降算法
In order to work off the algorithms called Stochastic gradient descent,
代价函数的定义有一点区别 我们定义参数θ
this vectors the cost function in a slightly different way then they define the cost of the parameter theta
关于训练样本(x(i),y(i))的代价 等于二分之一倍
with respect to a training example x(i), y(i) to be equal to one half times the squared error
我的假设h(x(i))跟实际输出y(i)的误差的平方
that my hypothesis incurs on that example, x(i), y(i).
因此这个代价函数值实际上测量的是我的假设在某个样本(x(i),y(i))上的表现
So this cost function term really measures how well is my hypothesis doing on a single example x(i), y(i).
你可能已经发现 总体的代价函数Jtrain可以被写成这样等效的形式
Now you notice that the overall cost function j train can now be written in this equivalent form.
Jtrain(θ)就是我的假设函数 在所有m个训练样本中的每一个样本(x(i),y(i))上的代价函数的平均值
So j train is just the average over my m training examples of the cost of my hypothesis on that example x(i), y(i).
用这样的方法应用到线性回归中
Armed with this view of the cost function for linear regression,
我来写出随机梯度下降的算法
let me now write out what Stochastic gradient descent does.
随机梯度下降法的第一步是将所有数据打乱
The first step of Stochastic gradient descent is to randomly shuffle the data set.
我说的随机打乱的意思是 将所有m个训练样本重新排列
So by that I just mean randomly shuffle, or randomly reorder your m training examples.
这就是标准的数据预处理过程 稍后我们再回来讲
It's sort of a standard pre-processing step, come back to this in a minute.
随机梯度下降的主要算法如下
But the main work of Stochastic gradient descent is then done in the following.
在i等于1到m中进行循环
We're going to repeat for i equals 1 through m.
也就是对所有m个训练样本进行遍历 然后进行如下更新
So we'll repeatedly scan through my training examples and perform the following update.
我们按照这样的公式进行更新
Gonna update the parameter theta j as theta j minus alpha times h of x(i) minus y(i) times x(i)j.
同样还是对所有j的值进行
And we're going to do this update as usual for all values of j.
不难发现 这一项实际上就是我们批量梯度下降算法中 求和式里面的那一部分
Now, you notice that this term over here is exactly what we had inside the summation for Batch gradient descent.
事实上 如果你数学比较好的话 你可以证明这一项 也就是这一项
In fact, for those of you that are calculus is possible to show that that term here, that's this term here,
是等于这个cost函数关于参数θj的偏微分
is equal to the partial derivative with respect to my parameter theta j of the cost of the parameters theta on x(i), y(i).
这个cost函数就是我们之前先定义的代价函数
Where cost is of course this thing that was defined previously.
最后画上大括号结束算法的循环
And just the wrap of the algorithm, let me close my curly braces over there.
随机梯度下降的做法实际上就是扫描所有的训练样本
So what Stochastic gradient descent is doing is it is actually scanning through the training examples.
首先是我的第一组训练样本(x(1),y(1))
And first it's gonna look at my first training example x(1), y(1).
然后只对这第一个训练样本 我们的梯度下降
And then looking at only this first example, it's gonna take like a basically a little gradient descent step
只对这第一个训练样本的代价函数进行
with respect to the cost of just this first training example.
换句话说 我们要关注第一个样本
So in other words, we're going to look at the first example
然后把参数θ稍微修改一点 使其对第一个训练样本的拟合变得好一点
and modify the parameters a little bit to fit just the first training example a little bit better.
完成这个内层循环以后 然后再转向第二个训练样本
Having done this inside this inner for-loop is then going to go on to the second training example.
然后还是一样 在参数空间中进步一小步
And what it's going to do there is take another little step in parameter space,
也就是稍微把参数修改一点 然后让它对第二个样本的拟合更好一点
so modify the parameters just a little bit to try to fit just a second training example a little bit better.
做完第二个 再转向第三个训练样本
Having done that, is then going to go onto my third training example.
同样还是修改参数 让它更好的拟合第三个训练样本
And modify the parameters to try to fit just the third training example a little bit better, and so on
以此类推 直到完成所有的训练集
until you know, you get through the entire training set.
因此这种重复循环会遍历整个训练集
And then this ultra repeat loop may cause it to take multiple passes over the entire training set.
从这个角度分析随机梯度下降算法 我们能更好地理解为什么一开始要随机打乱数据
This view of Stochastic gradient descent also motivates why we wanted to start by randomly shuffling the data set.
这保证了我们在扫描训练集时
This doesn't show us that when we scan through the training site here,
我们对训练集样本的访问时随机的顺序
that we end up visiting the training examples in some sort of randomly sorted order.
不管你的数据是否已经随机排列过 或者一开始就是某个奇怪的顺序
Depending on whether your data already came randomly sorted or whether it came originally sorted in some strange order,
实际上这一步能让你的随机梯度下降稍微快一些收敛
in practice this would just speed up the conversions to Stochastic gradient descent just a little bit.
所以为了保险起见 最好还是先把所有数据随机打乱一下
So in the interest of safety, it's usually better to randomly shuffle the data set if you aren't sure
如果你不知道是否已经随机排列过的话
if it came to you in randomly sorted order.
但随机梯度下降的更重要的一点是
But more importantly another view of Stochastic gradient descent is
跟批量梯度下降不同 随机梯度下降不需要对所有m个训练样本
that it's a lot like descent but rather than wait to sum up these gradient terms over all m training examples,
求和来得到梯度项 而是只需要对单个训练样本求出这个梯度项
what we're doing is we're taking this gradient term using just one single training example
我们已经在这个过程中开始优化参数了
and we're starting to make progress in improving the parameters already.
就不用把所有那3亿的美国人口普查的数据拿来遍历一遍
So rather than, you know, waiting 'till taking a path through all 300,000 United States Census records,
不需要对所有这些数据进行扫描
say, rather than needing to scan through all of the training examples
然后才一点点地修改参数 直到达到全局最小值
before we can modify the parameters a little bit and make progress towards a global minimum.
对随机梯度下降来说 我们只需要一次关注一个训练样本
For Stochastic gradient descent instead we just need to look at a single training example
而我们已经开始一点点把参数朝着全局最小值的方向进行修改了
and we're already starting to make progress in this case of parameters towards, moving the parameters towards the global minimum.
这里把这个算法再重新写一遍 第一步是打乱数据
So, here's the algorithm written out again where the first step is to randomly shuffle the data
第二步是算法的关键 是关于某个单一的训练样本(x(i),y(i))来对参数进行更新
and the second step is where the real work is done, where that's the update with respect to a single training example x(i), y(i).
让我们来看看 这个算法是如何更新参数θ的
So, let's see what this algorithm does to the parameters.
之前我们已经看到 当使用批量梯度下降的时候
Previously, we saw that when we are using Batch gradient descent,
需要考虑所有的训练样本数据
that is the algorithm that looks at all the training examples in time,
批量梯度下降的收敛过程 会倾向于一条近似的直线 一直找到全局最小值
Batch gradient descent will tend to, you know, take a reasonably straight line trajectory to get to the global minimum like that.
与此不同的是 在随机梯度下降中 每一次迭代都会更快
In contrast with Stochastic gradient descent every iteration is going to be much faster
因为我们不需要对所有训练样本进行求和
because we don't need to sum up over all the training examples.
每一次迭代只需要保证对一个训练样本拟合好就行了
But every iteration is just trying to fit single training example better.
所以 如果我们从这个点开始进行随机梯度下降的话
So, if we were to start stochastic gradient descent, oh, let's start stochastic gradient descent at a point like that.
第一次迭代 可能会让参数朝着这个方向移动
The first iteration, you know, may take the parameters in that direction and
然后第二次迭代 只考虑第二个训练样本
maybe the second iteration looking at just the second example maybe just by chance,
假如很不幸 我们朝向了一个错误的方向
we get more unlucky and actually head in a bad direction with the parameters like that.
第三次迭代 我们又尽力让参数修改到拟合第三组训练样本
In the third iteration where we tried to modify the parameters to fit just the third training examples better,
可能最终会得到这个方向
maybe we'll end up heading in that direction.
然后再考虑第四个训练样本 做同样的事 然后第五第六第七 等等
And then we'll look at the fourth training example and we will do that. The fifth example, sixth example, 7th and so on.
在你运行随机梯度下降的过程中 你会发现
And as you run Stochastic gradient descent, what you find is that
一般来讲 参数是朝着全局最小值的方向被更新的 但也不一定
it will generally move the parameters in the direction of the global minimum, but not always.
所以看起来它是以某个比较随机、迂回的路径在朝全局最小值逼近
And so take some more random-looking, circuitous path to watch the global minimum.
实际上 你运行随机梯度下降 和批量梯度下降 两种方法的收敛形式是不同的
And in fact as you run Stochastic gradient descent it doesn't actually converge in the same same sense as Batch gradient descent does
实际上随机梯度下降是在某个靠近全局最小值的区域内徘徊
and what it ends up doing is wandering around continuously in some region that's in some region close to the global minimum,
而不是直接逼近全局最小值并停留在那点
but it doesn't just get to the global minimum and stay there.
但实际上这并没有多大问题
But in practice this isn't a problem because, you know, so
只要参数最终移动到某个非常靠近全局最小值的区域内
long as the parameters end up in some region there maybe it is pretty close to the global minimum.
只要参数逼近到足够靠近全局最小值 这也会得出一个较为不错的假设
So, as parameters end up pretty close to the global minimum, that will be a pretty good hypothesis
所以 通常我们用随机梯度下降法
and so usually running Stochastic gradient descent
也能得到一个很接近全局最小值的参数 对于实际应用的目的来说 已经足够了
we get a parameter near the global minimum and that's good enough for, you know, essentially any, most practical purposes.
最后一点细节 在随机梯度下降中
Just one final detail. In Stochastic gradient descent,
我们有一个外层循环 它决定了内层循环的执行次数
we had this outer loop repeat which says to do this inner loop multiple times.
所以 外层循环应该执行多少次呢
So, how many times do we repeat this outer loop?
这取决于训练样本的大小 通常一次就够了
Depending on the size of the training set, doing this loop just a single time may be enough.
最多到10次 是比较典型的
And up to, you know, maybe 10 times may be typical
所以我们可以循环执行内层1到10次
so we may end up repeating this inner loop anywhere from once to ten times.
因此 如果我们有非常大量的数据 比如美国普查的人口数据
So if we have a you know, truly massive data set like the this US census gave us that example
我说的3亿人口数据的例子
that I've been talking about with 300 million examples,
所以每次你只需要考虑一个训练样本
it is possible that by the time you've taken just a single pass through your training set.
这里的i就是从1到3亿了
So, this is for i equals 1 through 300 million.
所以可能你每次只需要考虑一个训练样本
It's possible that by the time you've taken a single pass through your data set
你就能训练出非常好的假设
you might already have a perfectly good hypothesis.
这时 由于m非常大 那么内循环只用做一次就够了
In which case, you know, this inner loop you might need to do only once if m is very, very large.
但通常来说 循环1到10次都是非常合理的
But in general taking anywhere from 1 through 10 passes through your data set, you know, maybe fairly common.
但这还是取决于你训练样本的大小
But really it depends on the size of your training set.
如果你跟批量梯度下降比较一下的话
And if you contrast this to Batch gradient descent.
批量梯度下降在一步梯度下降的过程中
With Batch gradient descent, after taking a pass through your entire training set,
就需要考虑全部的训练样本
you would have taken just one single gradient descent steps.
所以批量梯度下降就是这样微小的一次次移动
So one of these little baby steps of gradient descent where you just take one small gradient descent step
这也是为什么随机梯度下降法要快得多
and this is why Stochastic gradient descent can be much faster.
这就是随机梯度下降了
So, that was the Stochastic gradient descent algorithm.
如果你做好了 你应该能把在很多学习算法中应用大量数据了
And if you implement it, hopefully that will allow you to scale up many of your learning algorithms
并且会得到更好的算法表现
to much bigger data sets and get much more performance that way.